<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<XSLTdocConfig>
  <Title>CiteProc</Title>
  <Introduction>
    <div class="section">
      <h2>Overview</h2>
      <p>CiteProc is a comprehensive solution for bibliographic and citation
        formatting. It consists of an easy-to-use XML citation style language
        (CSL), and the XSLT code to format documents based on them. In essence,
        it is designed to serve as an XML-based analog to BibTeX, but with
        dramatic improvements in ease-of-use, metadata flexibility, and
        international support.</p>
      <p>CiteProc reads the source document for citation references and collects
        the corresponding records from an external bibliographic data store, and
        then formats the bibliography and citations according to specifications
        in the CSL file.</p>
      <div class="image" align="center">
        <img src="images/citeproc-overview.png" width="320px"/>
        <p>CiteProc Overview</p>
      </div>
      <p>The data store can either be a flat XML file, or a server that supports
        HTTP-based XQuery or <a
          href="http://www.loc.gov/z3950/agency/zing/srw/sru.html">SRU</a>
        queries. SRU is a particularly promising new RESTful protocol that comes
        out of the library world, and which can provide a nice—<a
          href="http://sru.miketaylor.org.uk/">easily implemented</a>—standard
        around which a diversity of bibliographic solutions can interoperate.</p>
      <p>CiteProc is but one example of the possibilities opened up with SRU,
        where a user in North America can format their documents using
        bibliographic data stored on the other side of the world. Indeed,
        CiteProc is bundled with just such an example! The <a
          href="http://www.refbase.net">RefBase</a> project out of Germany
        recently added SRU support. The sample XML and XSLT files included here
        (samples/docbook-test-sru-refbase.xml and
        xslt/document/refbase-xhtml.xsl respectively) demonstrate how easy it is
        to add this support.</p>
    </div>
    <div class="section">
      <h2>Design</h2>
      <p>The core of the logic is embedded in the design of CSL, which has the
        following features:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>a tree-based design that mimics bibliographic metadata</li>
        <li>organized around references classes, rather than types</li>
        <li>modularizes formatting concerns</li>
      </ul>
      <p>At the core, CSL and CiteProc are both organized around structural
        classes (monograph, serial, etc.) rather than reference types or genres.
        CSL thus does not have the “generic” reference type definitions one
        finds in other style languages. Rather, CSL instead mandates definitions
        for three of the most common “types”: article, book, and chapter. These
        then serve as the class-specific fallback definitions. Indeed, most
        formatting ends up being handled by these generic definitions.</p>
      <p>This design decision addresses problems with type-based formatting
        systems like BibTeX or those in commmerical applications like Endnote,
        which tend to be fairly fragile and not very portable. In these systems,
        if a social scientist who frequently cites archival documents uses a
        style file created by a physical scientist, they will typically find
        they need to heavily edit the file in order to format their references.
        By moving to a class-based logic and modularizing formatting
        configuration as much as possible, styles become more portable.
        Likewise, retaining the familiar type-like interface is easier for users
        creating style files.</p>
    </div>
    <div class="section">
      <h2>Organization</h2>
      <p>The CiteProc code consists of one main stylesheet—called
        citeproc.xsl—which is imported into a standard document stylesheet.</p>
      <div class="image" align="center">
        <img src="images/citeproc-files.png" width="420px"/>
        <p>CiteProc file structure</p>
      </div>
    </div>
    <div class="section">
      <h2>Requirements</h2>
      <p>CiteProc is written in XSLT 2.0, and as such requires a compliant
        processor. At this point, this means <a href="http://www.saxonica.com"
          >Saxon 8</a>. In addition, it requires a data store for <a
          href="http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods">MODS</a> bibliographic data.
        CiteProc supports flatfile and server-based options, including both SRU
        and XQuery. The <a href="http://exist-db.org">eXist XML DB</a> is a good
        option. <a
          href="http://www.scripps.edu/~cdputnam/software/bibutils/bibutils.html"
          >Bibutils</a> is an excellent tool to convert from legacy formats like
        Endnote, RIS and BibTeX to MODS, and back. </p>
    </div>
    <div class="section">
      <h2>Useage</h2>
      <p>There are a few example document stylesheets in the xsl/document
        directory. For a basic local transformation using a flat file, use:</p>
      <code>
        <pre>java net.sf.saxon.Transform -o test.html samples/docbook-test.xml \
          xsl/document/dbng-xhtml.xsl citation-style="author-year" bibdb="flatfile"</pre>
      </code>
      <p>To use the remote SRU web service options, try the RefBase example like
        so:</p>
      <code>
        <pre>java net.sf.saxon.Transform -o test.html samples/docbook-test-sru-refbase.xml \
          xsl/document/refbase-xhtml.xsl</pre>
      </code>
      <p>The latter stylesheet is just a wrapper that imports the dbng-xhtml.xsl file and sets a few parameters.</p>
    </div>
    <div class="license">
      <p>CiteProc is free software, licensed under the <a
          href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/GPL/2.0/">CC-GNU GPL</a>.</p>
      <div class="image">
        <a href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/GPL/2.0/">
          <img alt="CC-GNU GPL" border="0" src="images/cc-GPL-a.png"/>
        </a>
      </div>
    </div>
  </Introduction>
  <!-- 
    The absolute or relative path to the target directory 
    where the HTML files are created. If a relative path
    is used it is always relative to the config file.
   -->
  <TargetDirectory path="./"/>
  <!-- 
    The absolute or relative path to the source directory.
    This is where the XSLT source files can be found.
    If a relative path is used it is always relative 
    to the config file.
   -->
  <SourceDirectory path="../xsl/"/>
  <!-- 
    A list of source code files which shall be documented. 
    Only stylesheets which are not included by another
    have to be listed here. The included stylesheets
    are found automatically by following the include or
    the import statements in the including stylesheet.
    Relative references are relative to the SourceDirectory
    defined above.
   -->
  <RootStylesheets>
    <File href="citeproc.xsl"/>
    <File href="document/refbase-xhtml.xsl"/>
    <File href="document/dbng-xhtml.xsl"/>
    <File href="document/dbng-latex.xsl"/>
  </RootStylesheets>
</XSLTdocConfig>
